{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "4.4","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Anti-Lea should be considered as a possible antibody","Anti-Lea may be a possible antibody, but further studies are needed","Anti-Lea is not a likely antibody because even Leb individuals secrete some Lea","Anti-Lea may be found in saliva but not detectable in serum"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-Lea is not a likely antibody because even Leb individuals secrete some Lea","explanation": "Anti-Lea is produced primarily by persons with the Le(a-b-) phenotype because Le(a-b+) persons do not form anti-Lea"},"question": "A patient has the Lewis phenotype Le(a-b-). An antibody panel reveals the presence of anti-Lea. Another patient with the phenotype Le(a-b+) has a positive antibody screen; however, a panel reveals no conclusive antibody. Should anti-Lea be considered a possibility for the patient with the Le(a-b+) phenotype?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood groups/2"},{"choices": ["Perform an enzyme panel","Neutralize the serum with saliva","Neutralize the serum with hydatid cyst fluid","Use dithiothreitol (DTT) to treat the panel cells"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Neutralize the serum with saliva","explanation": "Saliva from an individual with the Le gene contains the Lea antigen. This combines with anti-Lea, neutralizing the antibody. Panel cells treated with DTT (0.2M) lose reactivity with anti-K and other antibodies, but not anti-Lea. Hydatid cyst fluid neutralizes anti-P1"},"question": "A medical laboratory scientist (MLS) is having great difficulty resolving an antibody mixture. One of the antibodies is anti-Lea. This antibody is not clinically significant in this situation, but it needs to be removed to reveal the possible presence of an underlying antibody of clinical significance. What can be done?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood groups/3"},{"choices": ["Blood that is negative for Leb antigen","Blood that is negative for both Lea and Leb antigens","Blood that is positive for Leb antigen","Lewis antibodies are not clinically significant, so any type of blood may be given"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Blood that is negative for Leb antigen","explanation": "Lewis antibodies are generally not considered clinically significant unless they react at 37°C or at the IAT phase. The antibody must be honored in this scenario due to its reactivity at the IAT phase of testing"},"question": "What type of blood should be given to an individual who has anti-Leb that reacts 1+ at the IAT phase?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood group antibodies/3"},{"choices": ["Antigens are destroyed using bleach-treated cells","Dosage effect may be seen for both M and N antigens","Both M and N antigens are impossible to detect because of cross-interference","MN is a rare phenotype seldom found in routine antigen typing"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Dosage effect may be seen for both M and N antigens","explanation": "Dosage effect is the term used to describe the phenomenon of an antibody that reacts more strongly with homozygous cells than with heterozygous cells. Dosage effect is a characteristic of the genotype MN because the M and N antigens are both present on the same cell. This causes a weaker reaction than seen with RBCs of either the MM or NN genotype, which carry a greater amount of the corresponding antigen"},"question": "Which of the following statements is true concerning the MN genotype?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood groups/2"},{"choices": ["Anti-M may not allow detection of a clinically significant antibody","Compatible blood may not be found for the patient with a strongly reacting anti-M","Anti-M cannot be removed from serum","Anti-M may react with the patient’s own cells, causing a positive autocontrol"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-M may not allow detection of a clinically significant antibody","explanation": "Although anti-M may not be clinically significant, a strongly reacting anti-M that persists through to the IAT phase may interfere with detection of a clinically significant antibody that reacts only at IAT"},"question": "Anti-M is sometimes found with reactivity detected at the immediate spin (IS) phase that persists in strength to the IAT phase. What is the main testing problem with a strong anti-M?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood groups/2"},{"choices": ["The antibody attaches to RBCs at 4°C and causes hemolysis at 37°C","The antibody attaches to RBCs at 37°C and causes agglutination at the IAT phase","The antibody attaches to RBCs at 22°C and causes hemolysis at 37°C","The antibody attaches to RBCs and causes agglutination at the IAT phase"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The antibody attaches to RBCs at 4°C and causes hemolysis at 37°C","explanation": "The Donath-Landsteiner antibody has anti-P specificity with biphasic activity. The antibody attaches to RBCs at 4°C and then causes the RBCs to hemolyze when warmed to 37°C"},"question": "A patient is suspected of having paroxysmal cold hemoglobinuria (PCH). Which pattern of reactivity is characteristic of the Donath-Landsteiner antibody, which causes this condition?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood group antibodies/1"},{"choices": ["Neutralization with saliva","Agglutination with human milk","Combination with urine","Neutralization with hydatid cyst fluid"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Neutralization with hydatid cyst fluid","explanation": "Hydatid cyst fluid contains P1 substance, which can neutralize anti-P1 antibody"},"question": "How can interfering anti-P1 antibody be removed from a mixture of antibodies?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Blood group antibodies/1"},{"choices": ["Anti-Jka", "Anti-e", "Anti-K", "Anti-Fyb"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-e","explanation": "Anti-e is frequently implicated in cases of WAIHA. The corresponding antigen is characterized as high frequency in the Rh system and can mask the presence of other alloantibodies"},"question": "Which antibody is frequently seen in patients with warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia (WAIHA)?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood group antibodies/2"},{"choices": ["Anti-I", "Anti-i", "Anti-H", "Anti-p"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-I","explanation": "Adult cells contain mostly I antigen, and anti-I would react with all adult cells found on screen or panel cells. Cord blood cells, however, contain mostly i antigen and would test negative or only weakly positive with anti-I"},"question": "A patient’s antibody shows strong reactions in all test phases. All screen and panel cells are positive. Serum is then tested with a cord blood cell, and the reaction is negative. What antibody is suspected?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Antibody ID/2"},{"choices": ["Anti-K, anti-k, anti-Jsb","Anti-D, anti-e, anti-C","Anti-M, anti-N","Anti-Fya, anti-Fyb"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-M, anti-N","explanation": "Antibodies to the M and N antigens are IgM antibodies commonly found as cold agglutinins"},"question": "Which group of antibodies is commonly found as cold agglutinins?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood group antibodies/1"},{"choices": ["Anti-K", "Anti-Dia", "Anti-Sda", "Anti-s"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-Sda","explanation": "Anti-Sda characteristically gives a refractile mixed-field agglutination reaction in the IAT phase. The refractile characteristic is more evident under the microscope"},"question": "Which of the following antibodies characteristically gives a refractile mixed-field appearance?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Blood group antibodies/1"},{"choices": ["An antibody is ruled in","An antibody is ruled out","95% confidence that the correct antibody has been identified","95% confidence that the correct antibody has not been identified"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "95% confidence that the correct antibody has been identified","explanation": "The 3+3 rule ascertains correct identification of antibody at a confidence level of 95%. For this level to be met, reagent RBCs are found containing target antigen to suspected antibody that react in test phase; likewise, reagent RBCs devoid of antigen will not react in test phase"},"question": "What does the 3+3 rule ascertain?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Antibody ID/1"},{"choices": ["Often, because it is a high-frequency antibody","Rarely, because most individuals have the antigen and therefore would not develop the antibody","Depends on the population, because certain racial and ethnic groups show a higher frequency of anti-k","Impossible to determine without consulting regional blood group antigen charts"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Rarely, because most individuals have the antigen and therefore would not develop the antibody","explanation": "k antigen is found with a frequency of 99.8%; therefore, k-negative individuals are rare. Because of this, the occurrence of anti-k is also rare"},"question": "The k (Cellano) antigen is a high-frequency antigen and is found on most RBCs. How often would one expect to find the corresponding antibody?","reference": "Blood bank/Calculate/Hemotherapy/1"},{"choices": ["Lowering the pH of test serum","Running an enzyme panel","Using a thiol reagent","Running an LISS panel"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Running an enzyme panel","explanation": "Enzyme-treated cells will not react with Duffy antibodies. Rh antibodies react more strongly with enzyme-treated RBCs. An enzyme panel, therefore, would enhance reactivity of anti-e and destroy reactivity to anti-Fya"},"question": "Which procedure would help to distinguish between anti-e and anti-Fya in an antibody mixture?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Antibody ID/2"},{"choices": ["Detected at the IAT phase; may cause hemolytic disease of the fetus and newborn (HDFN) and hemolytic transfusion reactions","Not detected with enzyme-treated cells","Requires the IAT technique for detection; usually not associated with HDFN","Enhanced reactivity with enzyme-treated cells; may cause severe hemolytic transfusion reactions"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Detected at the IAT phase; may cause hemolytic disease of the fetus and newborn (HDFN) and hemolytic transfusion reactions","explanation": "Anti-Fya, anti-Jka, and anti-K are usually detected at IAT and all may cause HDFN and transfusion reactions that may be hemolytic. Reactivity with anti-Fya is lost with enzyme-treated RBCs, but reactivity with anti-Jka is enhanced with enzyme-treated cells. Reactivity with anti-K is unaffected by enzyme-treated cells"},"question": "Which characteristics are true of all three of the following antibodies: anti-Fya, anti-Jka, and anti-K?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Antibody ID/2"},{"choices": ["Crossmatch using units negative for Jka antigen","Crossmatch random units, since the antibody is not demonstrating","Request a new sample","Repeat the screen with enzyme-treated screening cells"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Crossmatch using units negative for Jka antigen","explanation": "The Kidd antibodies are notorious for disappearing from serum, yielding a negative result for the antibody screen. If a patient has a history of a Kidd antibody, blood must be crossmatched using antigen-negative units. If the patient is transfused with the corresponding antigen, an anamnestic response may occur with a subsequent hemolytic transfusion reaction"},"question": "A patient is admitted to the hospital. Medical records indicate that the patient has a history of anti-Jka. When you performed the type and screen, the type was O positive, and the screen was negative. You should:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Antibody ID/3"},{"choices": ["Antibody to a high-frequency antigen","Antibody to a low-frequency antigen","High titer low avidity (HTLA)","Anti-human leukocyte antigen (anti-HLA)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "High titer low avidity (HTLA)","explanation": "HTLA antibodies may persist in reaction strength, even when diluted. These antibodies are directed against high-frequency antigens (e.g., Ch<sup>a</sup>). They are not clinically significant but, when present, are responsible for a high incidence of incompatible crossmatches"},"question": "An MLS performs an antibody study and finds 1+ and weak positive reactions for several of the panel cells. The reactions do not fit a pattern. Several selected panels and a patient phenotype do not reveal any additional information. Serum is diluted and retested, but the same reactions persist. What type of antibody may be causing these results?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Antibody ID/3"},{"choices": ["Anti-Lea", "Anti-Lua", "Anti-Lub", "Anti-Xga"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-Lub","explanation": "Of the antibodies listed, only Lub is detected in the IAT phase, causes in vitro hemolysis, may cause HDFN, and does not react with DTT-treated cells"},"question": "An antibody is detected in a pregnant woman and is suspected of being the cause of fetal distress. The antibody reacts at the IAT phase but does not react with DTT-treated cells. This antibody causes in vitro hemolysis. What is the most likely antibody specificity?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Antibody ID/3"},{"choices": ["Plasma stored at 4°C for no longer than 24 hours","Serum stored at 4°C for no longer than 48 hours","Either serum or plasma stored at 20°C to 24°C no longer than 6 hours","Serum heated at 56°C for 30 minutes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Serum stored at 4°C for no longer than 48 hours","explanation": "Serum stored at 4°C for no longer than 48 hours preserves complement activity. Plasma is inappropriate because most anticoagulants chelate calcium needed for activation of complement. Heating the serum to 56°C destroys complement"},"question": "What sample is best for detecting complement-dependent antibodies?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Antibody ID/2"},{"choices": ["Anti-N", "Anti-A1", "Anti-Dia", "Anti-k"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-A1","explanation": "ABO antibodies are not detected by group O screening cells because O cells contain no A or B antigens"},"question": "Which antibody would not be detected by group O screening cells?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Antibody ID/1"},{"choices": ["Anti-Fyb","Anti-Jkb","Anti-e","Anti-c and anti-K"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-Jkb","explanation": "The pattern clearly fits that of anti-Jk<sup>b</sup>, an antibody that usually reacts best at IAT. The weaker reactions are caused by the dosage effect found on cells that are heterozygous for the Jk<sup>b</sup> antigen"},"question": "Refer to Panel 1. Which antibody is most likely implicated?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Antibody ID/2"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Testing for Antibodies"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}